<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Economy &#8211; ViralNewsBuzz</title>
	<atom:link href="https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/tag/economy/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 05:50:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Budget 2022 Was an Exercise With Misplaced Priorities</title>
		<link>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/why-budget-2022-was-an-exercise-with-misplaced-priorities/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=why-budget-2022-was-an-exercise-with-misplaced-priorities</link>
					<comments>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/why-budget-2022-was-an-exercise-with-misplaced-priorities/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abhishek Tiwari]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 09:14:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Indian Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/?p=153</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The budgetary exercise cannot be meaningful unless it addresses the primary concerns in an economy. Denials and rejections of the most pressing issue in the Indian economy today – which&#8230; ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote" style="font-size:25px"><p><strong><em>The budgetary exercise cannot be meaningful unless it addresses the primary concerns in an economy.</em></strong></p></blockquote>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="512" src="https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/K46PKF72KZJTTAPOAIN3MNAK6U-1200x600-1-1024x512.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-154" srcset="https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/K46PKF72KZJTTAPOAIN3MNAK6U-1200x600-1-1024x512.jpeg 1024w, https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/K46PKF72KZJTTAPOAIN3MNAK6U-1200x600-1-300x150.jpeg 300w, https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/K46PKF72KZJTTAPOAIN3MNAK6U-1200x600-1-768x384.jpeg 768w, https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/K46PKF72KZJTTAPOAIN3MNAK6U-1200x600-1.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Commuters travel in a train in Mumbai, India, February 1, 2022. Photo: Reuters/Francis Mascarenhas</figcaption></figure>



<p style="font-size:22px">Denials and rejections of the most pressing issue in the Indian economy today – which is providing employment as minimum livelihood options for the majority – need to be underscored in the current budget. Added to the above are the woes related to the cuts on the already small social sector spending for health and education, especially with the pandemic, along with reduced public offers of rural employment under MNREGA – not to speak of the continuing steep rise in food items.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">Following the most reliable statistics provided by the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), 65% of the labour force could not find any job – as indicated by the labour force participation ratio (LFPR) at 35% at its peak over the 21 day lockdown months of 2021. The sample covers all sections of the labour force other than migrants mostly located in construction sites, who are further affected. As compared to the employment figures of FY 2019-20 at 409 million, the number employed in December 2021, according to the CMIE, stood at 405 million. This amounted to a 3 million job loss as compared to the pre-pandemic period. Counting on the already low LFPR, the job requirements, according to same source, shot up to 8.5 million – a rather tall order when compared to the budget estimate of 60 lakh (or 0.6 million) jobs expected over the next FY.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">To explain the announced target for job creation as above, the budget in all probability relies on the focus on capex with a 25% enhancement in the budgeted allocation to Rs 7.5 trillion on infrastructures as an aid to job creation. That the multiplier effects of capital expenditure do not create demand for jobs instantly follow from the basics of macro-economic logic. The failure rests on investment (say capex) and the demand generated for jobs in the same units which usually are capital-intensive.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The next round of job availability comes when the newly employed persons in those units spend on consumption goods, creating additional consumption demand which leads to expansion of output with additional demand for labour. The sequence, which may continue, neither generates instantaneous labour demand nor is it adequate to fill up the much needed gap in the number of jobs which keep missing.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">Here, one can contrast the gains, small or large, as are available for the rich, primarily consisting of big capital, in the budget. One notices the big cut in surcharges on corporate earnings from 12% to 7%, obviously to subsidise those concerns. Taxes are reduced on co-operatives, which however may be of especial help to the losing concerns where money is often looted by the corrupt management. Announcement of further reductions in taxes include the Long term capital gains (LTCGs) on equities by capping those taxes down to 15%. This will be of considerable gain to large corporates as well as the rich individuals as who can afford to be risk-averse in the stock market.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The possibilities of hiding undisclosed income has been facilitated by extending the period of submitting returns to two full fiscal years. Finally, the passive role of the state towards the portfolio-led boom as well as volatility in the stock market has acted as a major force to widen income disparities between the rich and poor. Accepted as a norm under de-regulated finance with moderate to free capital flows in the market, the state exercises no concern for the resulting inequity as well as financial instability. Nor has the state any authority under de-regulated finance to manage the basic parameters in the domestic economy which include the interest rate or the exchange rate.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">A classic example of the related state of subordinate finance include the emergence of the “taper tantrum” on part of the US Fed as a measure to control US inflation. The rise in interest rates by the Fed may be responsible for a flight of short term capital from countries like India with serious consequences which include drop in official reserves, depreciation of the exchange rate and attempts on part of the RBI to stall the capital outflows by raising domestic interest rates. None of those measures indicate a state of autonomy on part of the monetary authorities, especially by forcing the tightening of domestic interest rates which will cause downslides in the real sector involving jobs and output growth.</p>



<div class="wp-block-group is-layout-flow"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container">
<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-4">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:100%">
<div class="wp-block-group is-layout-flow"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container"></div></div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<p style="font-size:22px">To amend the limitations of the so-called capex-led creation of jobs as projected in the recent budget one needs supplementary and remedial interventions to thwart the vicious cycle which is incapable to address the major issue of employment and related livelihoods. This can not be achieved by sheer expansions in the sum spent on capital goods in infrastructure projects, nor by temporary cash grants to the poverty-stricken people which can not be a substitute for jobs providing income on a continuing basis. Addressing the joblessness for the poor needs additions to MNREGA expenditure, not cuts as in the budget, and not just in the rural but also in urban areas. Creation of jobs also demands better deals for labour much of which has been scrapped by the newly initiated labour code in February 2020, just before the onset of the Pandemic. The measures also need to restore the rightful claims of casual labour and the migrants having no official status as employed persons.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">Finally, with privatisation of public sector units, the shortfall in job opportunities relative to demands for jobs can not be met by job offers with MNREGA alone. One needs a pro-active private sector sharing the responsibilities by using labour-intensive technology, which may need a carrot and stick policy on part of state using subsidies or taxes.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The budgetary exercise cannot be meaningful unless it addresses the primary concerns in an economy. For a democratically elected government the concern needs to focus on the well-being of people who constitute the electorate. A negation of above, as with the present situation in India, conflicts with the basic responsibilities of the state as well as the rightful claims of people including the workforce. The claims obviously include a sustainable livelihood with job openings and social security measures.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/why-budget-2022-was-an-exercise-with-misplaced-priorities/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>India&#8217;s recovery fastest, economy managed well, says Nirmala Sitharaman</title>
		<link>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/indias-recovery-fastest-economy-managed-well-says-nirmala-sitharaman/?utm_source=rss#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=indias-recovery-fastest-economy-managed-well-says-nirmala-sitharaman</link>
					<comments>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/indias-recovery-fastest-economy-managed-well-says-nirmala-sitharaman/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Abhishek Tiwari]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 09:06:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Indian Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[government]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/?p=149</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Finance minister Nirmala Sitharaman said on Thursday that India is the fastest growing economy despite the pandemic and asserted that the government managed the economy well. &#8220;Our recovery has been&#8230; ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote" style="font-size:25px"><p><strong><em>Finance minister Nirmala Sitharaman said on Thursday that India is the fastest growing economy despite the pandemic and asserted that the government managed the economy well.</em></strong></p></blockquote>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/budget-for-worlds-fastest-growing-economy-key-numbers-to-be-watched.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150" width="838" height="629"/><figcaption>Nirmala sitharaman</figcaption></figure>



<p style="font-size:22px">&#8220;Our recovery has been fastest and sustained among all economies&#8230;,&#8221; she said, adding that the recovery momentum will continue in the coming year. She said the government had focussed on capital expenditure because of its multiplier effect on the economy and to restore growth. &#8220;The Indian economy is projected to grow at 9% in the next financial year; the US is expected to grow at 4%,&#8221; she said, replying to the debate on the budget in the Lok Sabha.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">On divergence in growth estimates in the Economic Survey and the budget, she said the survey had used advanced estimates of the Central Statistics Office that had not taken into account the impact of the third wave of the pandemic. Sitharaman said the government thought it better to spend taxpayer money on capital expenditure, citing a Reserve Bank of India study that said every rupee so spent brought a return of ₹2.45 in the first year and ₹3.14 in the second.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The finance minister observed that while the government is borrowing money for capital expenditure, it is ensuring that revenue expenditure is rationalised, which she said will grow by slightly over 3% in FY23, showing a visible deceleration.</p>



<p style="font-size:25px"><strong>&#8216;MGNREGA is Demand-driven&#8217;</strong></p>



<p style="font-size:22px">Sitharaman countered allegations that the government has curtailed allocation on social security schemes, specifically the Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA). &#8220;MGNREGA is a demand-driven programme. As and when there is demand, through the supplementary demand for grants, we give the additional required amount,&#8221; Sitharaman added.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">She said banks had sanctioned loans worth ₹3.1 lakh crore under the Emergency Credit Line Guarantee Scheme for the MSME sector that was impacted by disruptions due to the pandemic. The scheme has been extended till March 2023. &#8220;Those MSMEs who still want to benefit out of it are welcome to use it&#8230;the amount of loan sanctioned under the ECLGS is ₹3.1 lakh crore and guarantee space is still ₹1.4 lakh crore,&#8221; she said in her 100-minute reply.</p>



<p style="font-size:25px"><strong>Andhakaal and Amritkaal</strong></p>



<p style="font-size:22px">Hitting out at the Congress party, Sitharaman said that the UPA term was India&#8217;s &#8216;Andhakaal&#8217;, citing double-digit inflation, poor management of foreign direct investment and rampant corruption.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">She claimed the government had managed the economic crisis better than UPA&#8217;s management of the global financial crisis in 2008-09 despite Covid being one of the worst events India had faced so far. She quoted data on key macroeconomic indicators after the financial crisis of 2008 and pandemic years to highlight better management of the pandemic-induced crisis.</p>



<p style="font-size:25px"><strong>&#8216;We Managed Economy Much Better&#8217;</strong></p>



<p style="font-size:22px">&#8220;Today, in spite of the crisis, reduction of GDP, Consumer Price Index is well contained, we have managed the economy much better,&#8221; the FM said, noting that despite disruption to the supply chain, inflation in 2020-21 was 6.2%, whereas in 2008-09, it was 9.1%.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The finance minister enlisted the initiatives and schemes of the Narendra Modi government, including Jan Dhan, rural electrification and Gati Shakti, adding: &#8220;All these schemes are paving a way towards Amritkaal.&#8221;</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p style="font-size:22px">Sitharaman highlighted the fact that 44 unicorns &#8211; startups with a valuation of $1 billion or more &#8211; have been identified in India between 2020 and 2021. &#8220;They have created wealth. They showcase India&#8217;s talent and innovation,&#8221; she said. The government, she said, had removed 25,000 compliances and repealed 1,500 laws for ease of doing business.</p>



<p style="font-size:25px"><strong>BSNL and Umbrella</strong></p>



<p style="font-size:22px">The finance minister said the revival of BSNL is due to the policies followed by the Modi government, while non-cooperative measures followed by the UPA had led to the decline of BSNL&#8217;s market share to 7.16% from 19% in 2015.</p>



<p style="font-size:22px">Defending the duty hike on umbrellas, Sitharaman said around 25 million umbrellas were being imported from one country and the measure will support the domestic industry.</p>



<script type="text/javascript">
	atOptions = {
		'key' : '7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696',
		'format' : 'iframe',
		'height' : 90,
		'width' : 728,
		'params' : {}
	};
	document.write('<scr' + 'ipt type="text/javascript" src="http' + (location.protocol === 'https:' ? 's' : '') + '://www.effectivedisplayformats.com/7913fb0db23f47ade957213e6ec50696/invoke.js"></scr' + 'ipt>');
</script>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abhishek-tiwaari.github.io/ViralNewsBuzz/indias-recovery-fastest-economy-managed-well-says-nirmala-sitharaman/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
